<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<document>

  <properties>
    <title>HttpClient News</title>
    <author email="dev@hc.apache.org">HttpClient Development Team</author>
    <author email="rwaldhoff@apache.org">Rodney Waldhoff</author>
    <author email="jsdever@apache.org">Jeff Dever</author>
    <revision>$Id$</revision>
  </properties>

  <body>
        <section name="16 December 2007 - HttpClient 3.1 website moved">
            <p>
              The website for HttpClient 3.1 has moved to the new domain
              of the HttpComponents top level project. The new location is:
              <br/>
              <a href="http://hc.apache.org/httpclient-3.x/">http://hc.apache.org/httpclient-3.x/</a>
            </p>
        </section>    
        <section name="13 December 2007 - Mailing lists moved">
            <p>
                As part of the move to a top level project, the HttpComponents
                team has moved the mailing lists to a new domain.
                The new mailing list names are:
            </p>
                <ul>
                <li><a href="mailto:httpclient-users@hc.apache.org">httpclient-users@hc.apache.org</a> - user list, renamed from httpclient-user@jakarta.apache.org
                </li>
                <li><a href="mailto:dev@hc.apache.org">dev@hc.apache.org</a> - developer list, renamed from httpcomponents-dev@jakarta.apache.org
                </li>
                </ul>
            <p>
                Subscribers to the old lists have been moved to the new ones.
                No action is required for posting and receiving mails on the
                lists, but you may have to update your mail filter rules
                with the new list names.
                Please see the HttpClient
                <a href="mail-lists.html">mailing list page</a> for 
                (un)subscription and archive details.
            </p>
        </section>    
        <section name="22 August 2007 - HttpClient 3.1 released">
            <p>
              HttpClient 3.1 has been released. This version adds a number improvements to the 
              connection management code and fixes a number of minor bugs. It is likely to be the 
              last non bug fixing release of the HttpClient 3.x codeline.
            </p>
        </section>    
        <section name="16 March 2007 - HttpClient 3.1-rc1 released">
            <p>
              HttpClient 3.1-rc1 has been released. This version fixes a number of issues
              found since 3.1-beta1. This release is expected to be the last one before 
              HttpClient 3.1 goes final.
            </p>
        </section>    
        <section name="30 October 2006 - HttpClient 3.1-beta1 released">
            <p>
              HttpClient 3.1-beta1 has been released. This version finalizes the RFC 2965 cookie 
              management API and adds a number of improvements to the HTTP connection management
              classes.
            </p>
        </section>    
        <section name="26 June 2006 - HttpClient 3.1-alpha1 released">
            <p>
              HttpClient 3.1-alpha1 has been released. This version adds support for the RFC 2965 cookie 
              management (also known as Cookie2 or port sensitive cookies). All upstream projects dependent 
              on HttpClient are strongly encouraged to review the new API and test new features for 
              compatibility with their products.
            </p>
        </section>    
        <section name="12 May 2006 - HttpClient issue tracking migrated to Jira">
            <p>
              HttpClient issue tracking has migrated from Bugzilla to Jira. Please do not enter new bug reports 
              and update exiting ones in Bugzilla. HttpComponents project will be using 
              <a href="http://issues.apache.org/jira/">Jira</a> to manage HttpClient related issues as of today. 
              Please use  <a href="http://issues.apache.org/jira/browse/HTTPCLIENT">this project</a> in Jira to 
              report new issues against HttpClient and search for reported ones. All existing issue reports can 
              be accessed in Jira by their original Bugzilla bug id.
            </p>
        </section>    
        <section name="08 May 2006 - HttpClient 3.0.1 released">
            <p>
              HttpClient 3.0.1 has been released. This version fixes a number of bugs found since the release of 3.0. 
              All HttpClient users are encouraged to upgrade.
            </p>
        </section>    
        <section name="27 February 2006 - HttpClient 2.x codebase declared 'End of Life'">
            <p>
                HttpClient 2.x will no longer be supported. There will be no more HttpClient 2.x releases
            </p>
        </section>    
        <section name="19 December 2005 - HttpClient 3.0 released">
            <p>
                The Jakarta Commons HttpClient project is pleased to announce the release of HttpClient 3.0.  
		This release fixes all of the bugs discovered in RC4. As before, we strongly recommend that all users upgrade 
		to HttpClient 3.0. Please <a href="downloads.html">download</a> and enjoy.
            </p>
	    <p>HttpClient 3.0 provides the following new features:
	        <ul>
   		    <li>Architecture
		        <ul>
			    <li>New preference architecture</li>
			    <li>Improved exception handling framework</li>
			    <li>Granular non-standards configuration and tracking</li>
			    <li>Improved HTTP Version configuration and tracking</li>
			    <li>Support for streaming entities</li>
			    <li>Support for tunneled HTTP proxies via the ProxyClient</li>
			    <li>Ability to abort execution of HTTP methods</li>
			</ul>
		     </li>
		     <li>Connection management
		        <ul>
			    <li>Support for closing idle connections</li>
			    <li>Support for JDK1.4 connect timeout through reflection</li>
			    <li>Support for connection manager shutdown</li>
			</ul>
		     </li>
		     <li>Authentication
		        <ul>
			    <li>Improved authentication framework</li>
			    <li>Plug-in mechanism for authentication modules</li>
			    <li>Interactive authentication support</li>
			    <li>Alternate authentication support</li>
			</ul>
		     </li>
		     <li>Cookie management
		        <ul>
			    <li>Cookie specification plug-in mechanism</li>
			    <li>'Ignore cookies' cookie policy</li>
			    <li>Improved Netscape cookie support</li>
			</ul>
		     </li>
		     <li>Redirects
		        <ul>
			    <li>Cross-site redirect support</li>
			</ul>
		     </li>
		</ul>
	    </p>
        </section>    
        <section name="11 October 2005 - HttpClient 3.0 RC4 released">
            <p>
                The Jakarta Commons HttpClient project is pleased to announce the fourth and hopefully final 
		release candidate of HttpClient 3.0.  RC4 fixes a number of hard to find bugs left over in the 
		previous release. We strongly recommend that all users upgrade 
		to HttpClient 3.0 RC4. Please <a href="downloads.html">download</a> and enjoy.
            </p>
        </section>    
        <section name="26 June 2005 - HttpClient 3.0 RC3 released">
            <p>
                The Jakarta Commons HttpClient project is pleased to announce the third release
                candidate of HttpClient 3.0.  RC3 has undergone quite a lot of user testing 
		and it fixes a number of bugs from RC2. We strongly recommend that all users upgrade 
		to HttpClient 3.0 RC3. Please <a href="downloads.html">download</a> and enjoy.
            </p>
        </section>    
        <section name="09 April 2005 - HttpClient 3.0 RC2 released">
            <p>
                The Jakarta Commons HttpClient project is pleased to announce the second release
                candidate of HttpClient 3.0. Several minor issues have been fixed since RC1 and 
                HttpClient 3.0 has made significant progess towards the final release. We are 
                confident HttpClient 3.0 is ready to replace HttpClient 2.0 as a production
                quality release. We strongly recommend upgrading to HttpClient 3.0. Please 
                <a href="downloads.html">download</a> and enjoy.
            </p>
        </section>    
        <section name="06 February 2005 - HttpClient 3.0 RC1 released">
            <p>
                We are pleased to announce the HttpClient 3.0 RC1 release.  The 3.0 API is frozen and
                all known bugs have been fixed.  Assuming no major problems are discovered in RC1 a final 3.0
                release will follow shortly.  We strongly encourage all current HttpClient users to start migrating. 
                Please <a href="downloads.html">download</a> and enjoy.
            </p>
        </section>    
        <section name="30 January 2005 - Source control switched to Subversion">
            <p>
                Along with the rest of the Jakarta Commons projects, HttpClient's version control
                has been switched to Subversion.  Please see the links below for more information:
                <ul>
                    <li><a href="http://www.apache.org/dev/version-control.html">Apache Subversion information</a></li>
                    <li><a href="http://wiki.apache.org/jakarta-commons/UsingSVN">Commons Subversion Wiki</a></li>
                    <li>HttpClient 3.0 repository - <a href="http://svn.apache.org/viewcvs.cgi/jakarta/commons/proper/httpclient/trunk/">http://svn.apache.org/viewcvs.cgi/jakarta/commons/proper/httpclient/trunk/</a></li>
                    <li>HttpClient 2.0 repository - <a href="http://svn.apache.org/viewcvs.cgi/jakarta/commons/proper/httpclient/branches/HTTPCLIENT_2_0_BRANCH/">http://svn.apache.org/viewcvs.cgi/jakarta/commons/proper/httpclient/branches/HTTPCLIENT_2_0_BRANCH/</a></li>
                </ul>
            </p>
        </section>
        <section name="21 November 2004 - HttpClient 3.0 beta1 released">
            <p>
                We are pleased to announce the first beta release of HttpClient 3.0.
                As of this release the 3.0 API is frozen.  We will now focus on creating additional
                documentation and test cases.  All current HttpClient 2.0 users are 
                strongly encouraged to migrate to 3.0. As always we encourage
                suggestions and bug reports. Please <a href="downloads.html">download</a> and enjoy.
            </p>
            <p>The HttpClient 3.0 site can be found 
               <a href="http://jakarta.apache.org/commons/httpclient/3.0/">here</a>.
            </p>
        </section>    
        <section name="23 October 2004 - New HttpClient mailing lists">
            <p>
                Starting today HttpClient has two new mailing lists for 
                developer and user discussion. People previously subscribed to <i>commons-httpclient-dev</i> have
                been automatically moved to the new developer mailing list.  People
                subscribed to <i>commons-user</i> who are interested in HttpClient will have 
                to join the HttpClient user mailing list manually.
            </p>
            <p>
                Please see the HttpClient <a href="mail-lists.html">mailing list page</a> for 
                (un)subscription and archive details.
            </p>
        </section>    
        <section name="11 October 2004 - HttpClient issue tracking in Bugzilla">
            <p>
                HttpClient project has taken a very important step toward becoming 
                a full-fledged Jakarta level project. From today, HttpClient is
                a separate project in Apache Bugzilla issue tracking system. It is no 
                longer a component of the Commons project. Please use the following
                details when filing bug reports for 2.0 and 3.0 branches of HttpClient:
              </p>
                <table border="0">
                  <tr> 
                    <td><strong>Product:</strong></td>
                    <td>HttpClient</td>
                  </tr> 
                  <tr> 
                    <td><strong>Component:</strong></td>
                    <td>Commons HttpClient</td>
                  </tr> 
                </table>
                <p>Use the following URL for convenience:
                <a href="http://issues.apache.org/bugzilla/enter_bug.cgi?product=HttpClient">
                  Jakarta HttpClient new issue report</a>.
               </p>
               <p>
                Currently HttpClient project is debating whether we should continue using Bugzilla
                as an issue tracking system or migrate to JIRA. 
                <a href="http://www.atlassian.com/software/jira/">JIRA</a> is a newer, more flexible 
                issue tracking system. However, <a href="http://www.atlassian.com/software/jira/">
                JIRA</a> is not open-source software. If you have a strong opinion on this matter, 
                please let us know.
            </p>
        </section>
        <section name="11 October 2004 - HttpClient 2.0.2 released">
            <p>
                We are pleased to announce the latest stable release of HttpClient, 
                version 2.0.2.  This release greatly improves the performance of executing 
                methods where the response contains little or no content.  Please see the 
                <a href="http://www.apache.org/dist/jakarta/commons/httpclient/RELEASE-NOTES-2.0.txt"
                >release notes</a> for more detail.
            </p>
            <p>
                Please <a href="downloads.html">download</a> and enjoy.
            </p>
        </section>
        <section name="19 September 2004 - HttpClient 3.0 alpha2 released">
            <p>
                We are pleased to announce the final alpha release of HttpClient 3.0.
                At this point HttpClient is fully feature-complete and is just a 
                few issue reports short of being code and documentation complete. 
                All of the important new features such as the new preferences 
                architecture and exception handling framework are completely documented. 
                We strongly encourage comment and criticism of the current API so we can
                have everything worked out by the first beta release. Following this 
                release the development effort will focus on stabilizing the 3.0 API 
                and adding more documentation. Depending on on how well this release is 
                received, as well as the quality and quantity of feedback, we are looking 
                at an API freeze in one to two months time.
            </p>
           <p>The preview of the HttpClient 3.0 site can be found 
             <a href="http://jakarta.apache.org/commons/httpclient/3.0/">here</a>.</p>

            <p>Please <a href="downloads.html">download</a> and enjoy.</p>
        </section>
      <section name="1 August 2004 - HttpClient 2.0.1 released">
        <p>We are pleased to announce the latest stable release of HttpClient, 
         version 2.0.1.  This release contains a few minor bug fixes and 
         enhancements.  Please see the <a 
         href="http://www.apache.org/dist/jakarta/commons/httpclient/RELEASE-NOTES-2.0.txt"
         >release notes</a> for more detail.
        </p>
        <p>
         Please <a href="downloads.html">download</a> and enjoy.
        </p>
    </section>
  
    <section name="17 May 2004 - HttpClient 3.0 alpha1 released">
        <p>We are pleased to announce the first HttpClient 3.0 release.
         HttpClient 3.0 provides a wealth of features and enhancements
         that did not make it into the 2.0 release, while preserving API
         compatibility as much as possible. In a relatively few cases
         <a href="http://svn.apache.org/viewcvs.cgi/jakarta/commons/proper/httpclient/trunk/API_CHANGES_3_0.txt?view=markup">API
         compatibility with HttpClient 2.0</a> could not maintained.
        </p>
        <p>   
         Noteworthy enhancements include:
         <ul>
          <li>New preference architecture</li>
          <li>Improved exception handling framework</li>
          <li>Granular non-standards configuration and tracking</li>
          <li>Improved authentication framework</li>
          <li>Plug-in mechanism for authentication modules</li>
          <li>Cookie specification plug-in mechanism</li>
          <li>Cross-site redirect support</li>
         </ul>
        </p>
        <p>
         We see our fellow Apache developers as well as other open-source
         projects already reliant on HttpClient as the primary target
         audience for this release. This is the right time to evaluate
         HttpClient 3.0 and give us some feedback, critique or other thought on
         the new API.  Please feel free to file requests for additional features.
        </p>
        <p>
         The goal of the second ALPHA release is to incorporate the feedback, polish 
         the API, and update documentation. The next ALPHA release will target the
         wider audience beyond the Apache Jakarta and Apache WS communities.
        </p>
        <p>
         Please <a href="downloads.html">download</a> and
         let us know what you think.
        </p>
    </section>

    <section name="16 April 2004 - Welcome Jakarta HttpClient!">
      <p>By the count 26 votes in favor, none against, Jakarta Commons HttpClient as been promoted 
      to the Jakarta sub-project level. The move to the Jakarta sub-project level is a next step in 
      HttpClient evolution which will result in many exiting changes and new developments. 
      So, stay tuned.</p>
    </section>

    <section name="15 February 2004 - HttpClient 2.0 Final released">
      <p>At last 2.0 final is upon us.  This release represents a great deal of work by quite
      	a number of people.  We would like to thank all of those who contributed to this 
      	release.</p>
      <p>Please <a href="downloads.html">download</a> and enjoy.</p>
    </section>

    <section name="16 January 2004 - HttpClient 2.0 Release Candidate 3 released">
      <p>While a final 2.0 release still eludes us, we have continued to make
       good progress.  This release fixes some significant bugs that crept into RC2.
       Assuming that there are no major bugs found in this release a final release should 
       follow shortly.</p>
    </section>

    <section name="13 October 2003 - HttpClient 2.0 Release Candidate 2 released">
      <p>Releasing a final version of HttpClient 2.0 by the end of Summer 2003, as 
       originally planned, was not possible. There were a significant number of minor 
       bugs reported against RC1. None of them were major, but verifying, fixing, and 
       testing simply took time more time than anticipated.  We are pleased to 
       announce the second release candidate of HttpClient 2.0 and hope to follow up 
       with a final release shortly.</p>
      <p>At the same time we have been busy working on our next release, currently 
       designated as 2.1. It it shaping up quite well. We already have a new preferences 
       architecture in place that will help us provide greater control over HttpClient 
       without polluting its API with too many options. We have also completely reworked 
       redirect/authentication/retry logic and can now support cross-host redirects, a 
       much complained about limitation of HttpClient 2.0.</p>
    </section>

    <section name="1 August 2003 - HttpClient 2.0 Release Candidate 1 released">
      <p>The <em>HttpClient 2.0 BETA</em> development phase has been
        concluded. The number of bugs discovered in the course of the BETA development
        was surprisingly low. We are confident that <em>HttpClient 2.0</em> has 
        reached the required level of maturity, and we hope to have a final 2.0
        release by the end of the Summer.</p>
    </section>

    <section name="02 July 2003 - HttpClient 2.0 Beta 2 released">
      <p>This release contains some minor bug fixes and documentation enhancements.
	Most likely this will be the final beta release before 2.0 Release Candidate 1.  As 
	always thank you to the HttpClient users and developers for their efforts.
	Please <a href="downloads.html">download</a> HttpClient 2.0 Beta 2 and
	enjoy.</p>
    </section>

    <section name="25 May 2003 - HttpClient 2.0 Beta 1 released">
      <p>This is the first feature-complete release of HttpClient 2.0.  A lot of
 	effort has been put into making this release functional, stable and 
	reliable. Many thanks to everyone who contributed code, time and testing. 
	Please <a href="downloads.html">download</a> HttpClient 2.0 Beta 1 and
	enjoy.</p>
      <p><b>Note:</b> The binary distributions were updated on 2 June, 2003 to 
        fix a problem with the original jar's MANIFEST.MF.  Using the original 
        HttpClient jar from within a servlet container or J2EE managed environment 
        may have caused some problems.</p>
    </section>

    <section name="25 February 2003 - HttpClient 2.0 Alpha 3 released">
      <p>This is an intermediate alpha release.  The build process used in
        the previous Alpha 2 changed from generating 4 build artifacts to
        a single distribution.  This one zip contains everything: all 
        the source, the binary jar, the logging dependancy, generated
        javadoc and required build files for Ant builds and JUnit tests.</p>
      <blockquote>
        "One zip to rule them all, one zip to find them, one zip to 
        bring them all and in the darkness bind them"</blockquote>
    </section>
    
    <section name="19 February, 2003 - Welcome new committer Michael Becke">
      <p>Mike been an active contributor for many months.  He has worked on a diverse range 
        of problems with high quality results.  In particular he is known for the massive
        HttpClient/HttpMultiClient merger that took place in December.</p>
      <p>Welcome to Middle Earth Mike!</p>
    </section>

    <section name="26 January 2003 - new mailing list archives">
      <p>There are two new mailing list archives of the commons-httpclient-dev
        mailing list.  It looks like someone up there is starting to like us!
        <ul>
          <li><a href="http://archives.apache.org/eyebrowse/SummarizeList?listId=128">
              http://archives.apache.org/eyebrowse/SummarizeList?listId=128</a></li>
          <li><a href="http://www.mail-archive.com/commons-httpclient-dev%40jakarta.apache.org/">
              http://www.mail-archive.com/commons-httpclient-dev%40jakarta.apache.org/</a></li>
        </ul>
      </p>
    </section>

    <section name="25 January 2003 - HttpClient 2.0 Alpha 2 released">
      <p>After many months and a great resurgence of developers, the new build
        of <em>HttpClient</em> is finally here.  The new group of developers has done
        extensive refactoring to move the project along the new vision.
        The code base has reached a significant level of maturity and we
        expect that the beta builds will come quickly and that the 
        final release of 2.0 is not far away!</p>

      <p>Also check out the new <em>HttpClient</em> logo!</p>
    </section>

    <section name="21 December, 2002 - Welcome new committer Oleg Kalnichevski">
      <p>Oleg is the first committer to be voted in on the dedicated httpclient 
        mailing list.  Welcome to the fellowship Olegolas!
      </p>
    </section>

    <section name="3 December, 2002 - HttpClient/HttpMultiClient merger">
      <p>The initial merger of the top level classes HttpClient and HttpMultiClient
        is complete.  Thanks for the patches and hard work from everyone 
        particularly to Michale Becke for supplying the primary patch.
      </p>
    </section>

    <section name="3 October, 2002 - commons-httpclient-dev mailing list">
      <p>The mailing list was renamed to be <b>commons-httpclient-dev</b>.
        Sorry for the confusion.
      </p>
    </section>

    <section name="12 July, 2002 - HttpClient 2.0 Release Planning">
      <p>The <em>HttpClient</em> project has go through some very active
        development leading up to Alpha 1 last year, but unfortunately 
        lost momentum shortly after that.  There is now renewed interest
        and greatly increased activity on the dev-commons mailing list.
        The committers and contributors are working on a new release plan
        for 2.0.
      </p>
      <p>The 2.0 release plan is expected to be posted to the mailing list for 
        review by July 22, 2002.
      </p>
    </section>

    <section name="5 October, 2001 - HttpClient 2.0 Alpha 1 Released">
      <p>
        The <em>HttpClient</em> revision 2.0 alpha 1 is
        available at
        <a href="http://jakarta.apache.org/builds/jakarta-commons/release/commons-httpclient/v2.0/">
          http://jakarta.apache.org/builds/jakarta-commons/release/commons-httpclient/v2.0/</a>.
      </p>
    </section>

    <section name="25 April, 2001 - HttpClient Proposal Accepted">
      <p>
        The <em>HttpClient</em> <a href="proposal.html">proposal</a>
        has been accepted by the
        <a href="http://jakarta.apache.org/commons">Jakarta Commons</a>
        team and the source has been moved into the
        <a href="http://svn.apache.org/viewcvs.cgi/jakarta/commons/proper/httpclient/trunk/">Subversion repository</a>.
      </p>
    </section>

    <section name="18 April, 2001 - HttpClient Proposed">
      <p>
        <em>HttpClient</em>, originally developed by the
        <a href="http://jakarta.apache.org/slide">Jakarta Slide</a>
        team, has been
        <a href="http://www.mail-archive.com/jakarta-commons@jakarta.apache.org/msg01153.html">proposed</a>
        as a <a href="http://jakarta.apache.org/commons">Jakarta Commons</a>
        component.
      </p>
    </section>
  </body>
</document>
