<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>

<document>
  <properties>
    <title>Threading</title>
    <author email="becke@u.washington.edu">Michael Becke</author>
    <revision>$Id$</revision>
  </properties>

  <body>
    <section name="Introduction">
      <p>This document provides an overview of how to use HttpClient safely from within a
      multi-threaded environment. It is broken down into the following main sections: </p>
      <ul>
      	<li><a href="#MultiThreadedHttpConnectionManager">MultiThreadedHttpConnectionManager</a></li>
	    <li><a href="#Connection Release">Connection Release</a></li>
	  </ul>
      <p>Please see the <a href="http://svn.apache.org/viewvc/httpcomponents/oac.hc3x/trunk/src/examples/MultiThreadedExample.java?view=markup">MultiThreadedExample</a>
      	for a concrete example.</p>
    </section>

    <section name="MultiThreadedHttpConnectionManager">
      <p>The main reason for using multiple theads in HttpClient is to allow the
      	execution of multiple methods at once (Simultaniously downloading the latest builds of HttpClient and 
      	Tomcat for example). During execution each method uses an instance of an HttpConnection. 
      	Since connections can only be safely used from a single thread and method at a time and 
      	are a finite resource, we need to ensure that connections are properly allocated to the methods that require them. 
      	This job goes to the <a href="apidocs/org/apache/commons/httpclient/MultiThreadedHttpConnectionManager.html">MultiThreadedHttpConnectionManager</a>.</p>
      <p>To get started one must create an instance of the MultiThreadedHttpConnectionManager
      	and give it to an HttpClient.  This looks something like:</p>
      <source><![CDATA[
      	MultiThreadedHttpConnectionManager connectionManager = 
      		new MultiThreadedHttpConnectionManager();
      	HttpClient client = new HttpClient(connectionManager);
      ]]></source>
      <p>This instance of HttpClient can now be used to execute multiple methods from multiple 
      	threads. Each subsequent call to HttpClient.executeMethod() will go to the connection 
      	manager and ask for an instance of HttpConnection.  This connection will be checked out
      	to the method and as a result it must also be returned.  More on this below in <b>Connection Release</b>.</p>
      	
      <subsection name="Options">
      	<p>The MultiThreadedHttpConnectionManager supports the following options:</p>
      	<table>
      	  <tr>
      	  	<td>connectionStaleCheckingEnabled</td>
      	  	<td>The <tt>connectionStaleCheckingEnabled</tt> flag to set on all created connections.  This value 
      	  	should be left <tt>true</tt> except in special circumstances.  Consult the 
      	  	<a href="apidocs/org/apache/commons/httpclient/HttpConnection.html#setStaleCheckingEnabled(boolean)">HttpConnection</a> 
      	  	docs for more detail.</td>
      	  </tr>
      	  <tr>
      	    <td>maxConnectionsPerHost</td>
      	    <td>The maximum number of connections that will be created for any particular 
      	      HostConfiguration. Defaults to 2.</td>
      	  </tr>
      	  <tr>
      	    <td>maxTotalConnections</td>
      	    <td>The maximum number of active connections. Defaults to 20.</td>
      	  </tr>
      	</table>
      	<p>In general the connection manager makes an attempt to reuse connections 
      	  for a particular host while still allowing different connections to
          be used simultaneously.  Connection are reclaimed using a least recently
      	  used approach.</p>
      </subsection>
    </section>

    <section name="Connection Release">
      <p>One main side effect of connection management is that connections must 
      	be manually released when no longer used.  This is due to the fact 
      	that HttpClient cannot determine when a method is no longer using its connection.  
      	This occurs because a method's response body is not read directly by
      	HttpClient, but by the application using HttpClient.  When the response is read it must obviously make use of the method's 
      	connection.  Thus, a connection cannot be released from a method until the method's 
      	response body is read which is after HttpClient finishes executing the
        method.  The application therefore must manually release the
        connection by calling releaseConnection() on the method after the
        response body has been read.  To safely ensure 
      	connection release HttpClient should be used in the following manner:</p>
      	
      <source><![CDATA[

      	MultiThreadedHttpConnectionManager connectionManager = 
      		new MultiThreadedHttpConnectionManager();
      	HttpClient client = new HttpClient(connectionManager);
			...
        // and then from inside some thread executing a method
        GetMethod get = new GetMethod("http://httpcomponents.apache.org/");
        try {
            client.executeMethod(get);
            // print response to stdout
            System.out.println(get.getResponseBodyAsStream());
        } finally {
            // be sure the connection is released back to the connection 
            // manager
            get.releaseConnection();
        }
    ]]></source>

      <p>Particularly, notice that the connection is released regardless of
      what the result of executing the method was or whether or not an
      exception was thrown.  For every call to HttpClient.executeMethod there
      must be a matching call to method.releaseConnection().</p>
    </section>
  </body>
</document>
